just get a brief recap of the general
parameters for an excellent power and
strength training
program okay let me hit you with these
rapid fire and then you can maybe come
ask questions along that remember those
modifiable variables okay so let's go
through them in order and then what they
mean specifically for power versus
strength so modifiable variable number
one is called choice so which exercises
do I select for strength in for power or
speed or strength we want to select
compound movements you don't often see
people doing maximum strength work for
like a tricep Kickback right it's
typically multiple joint movements and
typically
complex um movements in selecting these
compound movements we generally want to
actually think about exercise selection
of movements rather than muscle groups
so this is an important distinction
because we'll see this is a different
answer when we get hypertrophy what I
mean by that is when we think about
again strength training we tend to think
about bodybuilding Concepts we go to the
gym and we do things like I got to make
sure I get my chest today and I got to
make sure I get my hamstrings and now
you're selecting exercises based on a
muscle you want to work for strength
development and power we want to think
about movements rather than individual
muscle groups so there should be like
things like I need to train explosive
hip extension which is like a a a
vertical jump or something like that I I
want to train pushing or pulling
movements or I want to Tain rot I want
to train rotation which is a whole area
we haven't gotten into which is very
important for overall health and
wellness longevity so we want to select
big movements by the muscle the movement
patterns that we want to introduce and
we just want to select a reasonable
balance between these I don't care what
the exact ratio is you just don't want
to go an entire six months without doing
anything in this rotational area or an
entire you know8 to 10 weeks without
doing something um uh that's a lower
body hinge right so any number of
examples there so just think about the
rough movement patterns upper and lower
push and pull uh and then some sort of
rotation that puts you in a pretty good
spot if you're using 3x five method and
you're going to pick as little as three
exercises just pick one from each one of
those group pick a rotation pick a a
push and pick a pull we select our
exercises based on that we generally
then CA because of that as a case we
don't worry about things like Ecentric
versus concentric because you're dally
doing a whole body athletic movement
right which the Ecentric concentric
portion is going to be folded into that
you really can't separate them out right
so that's exercise Choice our first
variable the next one is exercise order
so because the everything driving power
and strength is quality based you want
to do these at the beginning of your
workout you would not want to do
anything fatiguing before this so no
cardiovascular training no other uh
repetition to failure stuff if you do
those before and now you're slower all
you've done is practice getting slower
and and so these need to be done when
you're fresh you also need to do them
when you're very fresh because they are
the most neurologically demanding
they're complicated they tend to have
multiple steps and they're often in
multiple planes and coordination is a
difficult thing and if you're trying to
do all that at maximum speed your
nervous system needs to be tremendously
fresh and so any amount of fatigue here
is only going to compromise results um
to kind of recap that uh one of the
major mistakes when training for
strength and especially power is people
worry way too much about fatigue those
things should not be part of the
equation in fact if they are that's a
very good sign you're not doing this
correctly these are non fatiguing
movements especially speed and power the
next one after that is volume and we
sort of hit volume and intensity which
is the other one um we we talked about
that the volume is basically identical
between power and strength um the the
general number we're going to look at
here is something like three to 20 sets
total per workout per workout um but
that would be like 20 would be a little
bit of a special case three to five is
what I told you earlier right I'm just
saying like sometimes you can actually
go quite higher in cases but that's the
general range and once somebody finishes
the 3x5 workout for power or strength if
they decide they want to throw in some
calf raises and curls and totally a
forearm work or a little bit of joggy on
the treadmill or something that's okay
absolutely there is you have very little
little risk of interference for things
like speed and power strength you have a
little bit of a risk only because now
you're introducing fatigue which if
you're really pushing strength that
might compromise your recovery so that
that's a that's a really nice uh heris
to pay attention to is you can but just
be careful Energy starts to matter at
that point um if you're really truly
trying to maximize strength you would do
nothing at all outside of that training
um if you're just like I kind of want to
get stronger and some other things and
you're willing to lose strength you know
5% of your strength gains then you're
you're totally fine um the same can be
said by the way for super setting so
super setting is an idea that says like
wait a minute you're telling me dude I
got to take five minutes in between each
set well that's not so much a problem
nowadays with um smartphones because
people are filling their interet
intervals with social media and texting
correct you you don't really have to go
that long in fact there was actually a
study that came out in the last month
that showed you know like really 2
minutes is probably sufficient for most
people having said that if you really
are trying to push maximum strength
adaptations like three to five is very
very reasonable um you're those training
sessions are long because you have to
take you're spending more time not doing
anything than you aren't doing something
but you're trying to maximize quality so
that's just sort of like part and parcel
um if you're not super worried about it
you can actually do super setting which
is let's imagine again you're going to
do some some lunges and while your legs
are resting doing their 3 to 5 minutes
you can go over and do an upper body row
or pull and when your upper body's
resting you're going back to legs so
that really Cuts your time in half is it
ideal no we actually ran a study uh
maybe 10 years ago in our lab and we
looked at that specifically and we did
see a reduction in strength performance
in the super setting group relative to
the group who did not
superet the question then it becomes
like is it enough for you to care so if
you were if I were to say hey I can cut
an hour off of your workout time but you
will lose 5% of your strength gain
almost everyone would take that exchange
with the exception of people who are
getting close to competition or really
trying to set a new lifetime PR or
something then you might say no I don't
want any interference there that last
little margin is what I care about give
me the extra rest great so it's not a
does it work does it not work it's
always a what are you willing to give up
uh versus get the last one is frequency
and we've already sort of indirectly
talked about that where frequency can be
as high as you'd like in this area it
really depends on your recovery if
you're really truly pushing maximum
strength you probably do need a few days
to recover although that's dependent
upon you but speed and power can be done
multiple times a day almost every day
basically um the one exception would be
maximum sprinting speed you need to be
careful there for things like hamstring
uh and injury especially if you're
pretty fast so you want to be a little
bit cautious of that but if you're doing
easier movements um like medicine ball
throws or kettle bell swings or
something you could do those quite often
as long as the volume is is staying
pretty low last little piece here is
progression how do I progress over time
so I mentioned this earlier but just
wanted to fill this Gap right back in
before we head over to hypert tree which
is 3 to 5% increase per week of
intensity in general um and you can do
upwards of about 5% increase in volume
per week over time and I generally
recommend running that for uh at longest
eight weeks but probably most
realistically you want to go about five
weeks or so and then have some sort of a
D Lo or back off week if you do that
you're you're generally going to be a
pretty good spot click the link in our
bio to get instant and free access to
our hypertrophy highlights fireside chat
which is Dan and I discussing really
personal aspects of how we go about
programming for muscle hypertrophy in
that chat you're going to hear Dan and I
talk about our own experiences working
with clients who are trying to add
muscle mass and especially you're going
to hear us tell some stories that you've
never heard us talk about in any podcast
ever before this is not something you're
going to want to miss
oh